Ben Phelper papers, Inclusive: 1943-1981, undated, Bulk: 1943-1945, undated
Baylor University Libraries
Ben Phelper papers
Inclusive: 1943-1981, undated, Bulk: 1943-1945, undated
Baylor University Libraries https://www.baylor.edu/library/
1584
Phelper, Ben Reynolds
4 document boxes
The Ben Phelper papers contain typed copies of diaries kept by Phelper while in a World War II prisoner of war camp, plus correspondence, newsletters, and unpublished manuscripts.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Ben Herbert Phelper, was born in 1916. His early education is unknown, but in his twenties, he began work as an illustrator for Walt Disney. Phelper enlisted in the United States Air Force in Los Angeles at the age of 25, and was recruited into military intelligence to organize United States prisoners in German prisoner of war camps. After re-enlisting in Chicago under the name Ben Phelper as directed, he completed two years of training in the United States and England. While on a bombing mission in Germany, he was shot down, captured, and sent to Kems-on-the-Danube prison camp in Austria. For two years, Phelper organized and led guerilla raids against the German war effort while still a prisoner. When he was freed in 1945 May 3, he offered copies of diaries and over 1,000 photographs from his time as a prisoner to the United States military. They kept the photographs, but allowed him to keep the diaries. Years later, two other prisoners of war claimed that they had been in a pact with Phelper to jointly accumulate materials and co-write a book about their prisoner of war experiences, but that Phelper took all the photographs and diaries at the end of the war.
Back in the United States, he wrote about his experiences during the war in a number of books, and compiled information about the John F. Kennedy assassination. Phelper married Marjorie Anne Gale in 1950. In 1964, he was accused of taking obscene photographs and sending them through the mail. He carried the case all the way to the Supreme Court, but it is unknown if he won the case or not. Phelper retired from the Air Force in 1971 and moved to Texas permanently. Ben Phelper passed away on 1993 September 29, and is buried in Fort Sam Houston National Cemetery.
Scope and Content
The Ben Phelper papers include published books, unpublished drafts, newsletters, correspondence, subject files, and materials about World War II and prisoners of war. The typed manuscripts of Phelper’s prisoner of war diaries are the closest available documents to the original, as the original diaries were lost in a housefire. Unpublished manuscripts include a document on the John F. Kennedy assassination, as Phelper asserted that he knew who was responsible for the assassination. Another unpublished manuscript details the various groups that Phelper believed were out to murder him.
Arrangement
The Ben Phelper papers were arranged in folders with titles in four boxes prior to current processing.
Currently, the Ben Phelper papers include two series: I. World War II Prisoner of War and II. Personal.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 1584. Acquired 1977-03-31
Related Resources
Related references
Find A Grave, Inc. “Ben H. Phelper.” Memorial #1077699. Accessed on 2021 July 15.
Lutgen, Bob. “Ben Phelper, Former Spy, Says He’s Coming in from the Cold.” The Eagle, 1978 July 3.
“Obscenity Conviction Review OK.” Oakland Tribune, 1966 October 17.
“Richardson Man Charged in Mailing Obscene Pictures.” Lubbock Avalanche-Journal, 1964 January 24.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Phelper, Ben H.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945 -- Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Veterans -- United States.
Genres
Correspondence.; Diaries.; Manuscripts.; Newsletters.
- World War II Prisoner of War, 1943-1981, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Unknown.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains a typed copy of Phelper's World War II prisoner of war diaries, various books and plays based on them, and accompanying resources. This series is in good condition.
  - Typed POW Diary (1 of 5), 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Typed POW Diary (2 of 5), 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Typed POW Diary (3 of 5), 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Typed POW Diary (4 of 5), 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Typed POW Diary (5 of 5), 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Typed POW Diary (1 of 4), 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Typed POW Diary (2 of 4), 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Typed POW Diary (3 of 4), 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Typed POW Diary (4 of 4), 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - POW Diary, manuscript, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Information about POW Diaries, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Shot Down, softcover book, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Shot Down, hardcover book, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - The Sweat Box, softcover book, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Shot Down, The Sweat Box softcover book, 1947, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Visual Tour of Prison Camp, softcover book, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Stalag, softcover book, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Stalag 17B, softcover book, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Stalag 17" play, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Red Cross POW Bulletins (1 of 2), 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Red Cross POW Bulletins (2 of 2), 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - B-17 Fortress at War book, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Personal, 1943-1978, undated; 2
  This series contains correspondence, newsletters, unpublished manuscripts written by Phelper, and a published manuscript that Phelper helped edit. This series is in good condition.
  - Harry Braverman, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Wright Patman, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - C.W. Brown II, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Magda Andritsch, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Richard S. Schweiker, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Frank Church, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Efforts to help ex-POWs, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ben Phelper to Relatives (1 of 2), 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ben Phelper to Relatives (1 of 2), 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence (1 of 2), 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Watchdog Newsletters, 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Confederate Air Force (1 of 2), 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Confederate Air Force (2 of 2), 1961-1963 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Red, White, and Black, book, 1964, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "The Texas Bird," book, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Hit Attempts" by Ben Phelper (1 of 2), circa 1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Hit Attempts" by Ben Phelper (2 of 2), circa 1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Hit Attempts by the Mafia or Crooked Businessmen" (1 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Hit Attempts by the Mafia or Crooked Businessmen" (2 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Investigation of the John F. Kennedy Assassination (1 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Investigation of the John F. Kennedy Assassination (1 of 2), undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Get the Hell Out of Texas," First Draft (1 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Get the Hell Out of Texas," First Draft (2 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Get the Hell Out of Texas," First Draft (3 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Get the Hell Out of Texas," First Draft (4 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Get the Hell Out of Texas," First Draft (5 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Get the Hell Out of Texas," Typed Manuscript (1 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Get the Hell Out of Texas," Typed Manuscript (2 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Get the Hell Out of Texas," Typed Manuscript (3 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Get the Hell Out of Texas," Typed Manuscript (4 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Get the Hell Out of Texas," Typed Manuscript (5 of 5), undated (Box 4, Folder 14)